(wind blowing)
(uplifting piano music)
- Oh, that's nice.
- We all have demons.
We all have dark days.
I believe we all even have
things we're running from.
I do what I do, because
I've been lucky enough
to identify two disciplines in my life
that I absolutely love to do.
And, for me, these two things
are my strongest talismans
against keeping ahead of my demons.
When I'm climbing, it's
like force meditation.
I'm in the moment, and then I shoot things
that are fast-paced environments.
You know, a 12-hour day,
freezing my ass off,
and I'm gonna miss that one
shot if I'm not in the zone.
Pefect, Audrey.
- Alright.
- Amazing, okay.
And then, something like
it's definitely flicked
in my head one day when I was climbing,
I realized that there were a lot
of active climbers out there,
and there were a lot of really
world-class photographers,
but there was very few
crossing over those two realms.
Like, really putting in the effort
and shooting with intention.
That was the biggest thing for me.
That was the biggest inspiration for me.
I really felt like there was a gap there,
and that I was just
excited to share and film.
I'm never more excited
than after I've just finished a route,
then when I get home and
I'm uploading all my files,
and I get to start editing what
I've captured over that day.
Just inciting that stoke
and that passion in people
is big to me, because
that was incited in me.
That was given to me through other people,
and other creatives in the valley,
and that totally changed my life.
In the beginning it was just like, yeah,
it was just like what
everyone does, right?
Little point and shoot camera,
no intention, no effort.
It was a little Olympus Tough.
I was just shooting whatever
compositions I could get
while climbing whatever
I was normally climbing.
- When I first started
getting out with John,
his skill level, I would
say, it was pretty minimal,
because he was handling
DSLRs, digital cameras,
for the first time.
He was just starting from
scratch, more or less.
(alarm clock blaring)
- The way I've lived this last year
stems from my one main goal this year,
and that was to be as
available and free as possible
to climb and shoot whenever I needed to,
and that meant if a high profile climber
wanted me to do something with them,
I'd be able to say yes, drop
of the hat, no matter what.
If the light was perfect
and all conditions aligned,
and you know, light just turning yellow,
and fresh snowfall on a castle, whatever.
I wanted to be available this year
to get after any opportunity
and say yes to every single opportunity,
and that meant work as
absolutely minimal as possible,
which translates to
earning next to no money,
and getting out all the time.
(uplifting music)
Then I got really psyched
on sharing the images,
and I noticed people were
responding really well to them,
and people like friends back
home in Australia, New Zealand,
Canada, they liked the
words attached to them,
they liked the insight into
the climbing lifestyle,
and you see the hundreds of comments,
people wanting to go and do
that route after you've shot it,
and getting so psyched on climbing again,
or being inspired to start
taking their camera out
on the climbs that they're doing.
That, in turn, inspired me to, you know,
well, how can I tell, how can
I share this more accurately,
or in a way to invoke more emotion,
or that people can actually
see what's going on.
(uplifting music)
- I think if one didn't know John,
and they just saw his social media image,
they would think he's been
at this for a long time,
and is doing really well with it.
- One of the hardest
things with social media
is that you feel kind of a
pressure to only report the good.
You wanna come back from a day,
and you have this epic image that you love
and that you wanna share,
and you know, you don't to attach,
oh, had a shitty day, I broke my lens.
I feel really down.
Man, I'm so broke.
You wanna post something
about how epic the photo is that you got.
You know, this is so rad.
Look at this cool, such a great day.
I can't even remember how many times
my captions on my photos have started with
such a great day or such a fun day.
There's a formula to what's
popular on social media.
People shoot that formula,
and they portray that perfect
life to market themselves.
I think it's just really
negative for our mental health,
and for society for
everyone to constantly be
negatively envious of
other people's lifestyles,
because it's bullshit.
You don't see the reality.
You don't see their pressure,
and you don't see the bill paying.
You don't see the fights, you
don't see any of that crap.
You just see hammocks, and
perfect climbs, and summit days,
and it just kind of feels like a lie.
Like, none of us live perfect lives.
None of us are always happy.
None of us always get the
dream jobs or the dream gigs.
I think the reality is social
media just makes us feel down
and anxious, and like we're
missing out on something.
- There's a huge discrepancy, I think,
between what it's like to
do photography for work,
and what the general public thinks it is.
- You put images out there,
and people make up their own mind
about what your life is like,
and sometimes it's really
far from the truth.
- People can play with social media a lot.
There can be a lot of
altered truths out there,
and same with photography.
I think there's,
you know, it must be really
hard as a photographer to
always have a pure image.
- It's nice if you're able to be honest,
and convey that it's not always just
everyday is not the best day all the time,
but at the same time, yeah,
you have to put your best stuff out there.
Even if it's unwillingly,
you're still maybe misleading
people a little bit.
- It's a juggling act of
truth and selling yourself.
There I was shooting everyday,
and everyone was under the impression
that I was getting paid for this,
that all my personal creative
projects were paid gigs,
and I was living the dream, and
I was doing what I wanna do,
and hanging out with my friends everyday,
and climbing and shooting,
and the reality is I was making money
from like 10% of that stuff.
Yeah, after a while,
I just thought of this series of portraits
that I could do to kind of
maybe show the reality of this.
It's not paid gigs, and
it's late nights editing,
and it's not glamorous.
And so, to do that, my friends,
I was house-sitting for my
friend and sat down with his dog,
and staged some portraits
there where I was eating
a pack of ramen for dinner,
and she was eating one little dog treat.
Yeah, it wasn't far from
the truth for months there.
It was touch and go.
And, I was just...
uncomfortable with what
people thought I was,
and thought the life that I lived,
and I just wanted to
shed some truth on that.
That was a shot I took of my cousin
at a burnt out observatory
back in Australia.
When I shot that photo,
I had all of these themes
running through my head,
because the inside of the observatory
was burnt out and concrete,
and stark and rundown,
and outside was this beautiful blue sky,
green grass, sunny day,
and it was like a reminder
to friends and to people,
like hey, we all feel shitty.
No one's life is perfect.
I've suffered from depression
like a lot of people, I'm sure,
and just...
don't believe in the crap.
I don't believe in that myth.
That got more hits and more
comments and more feedback
than any post I've ever done.
The more I get involved in social media,
the more I feel responsible
to break down those barriers
and that facade.
- As an athlete,
I don't wanna be on a picture
that I haven't climbed.
I don't wanna have a shot
of me doing something
that I haven't done,
or that the rope's taken
out of from above me,
or the gears erased,
or something like that.
I want it to be a real
photo of me doing something
that I've achieved,
otherwise I don't want it to be out there.
That's something I stand by,
and I feel like John's on the same page
with his photography.
- I think if you can
instill real storytelling,
and honesty in social
media in any way possible
in whatever you do, whatever it is,
if you can find that balance
and have a truly loving,
respectful, honest
community following you,
then that to me is, you know,
500 of those people are
worth 10 million people
who believe in a myth.
Whoa, wow, this looks amazing.
- Where is John gonna take it from here?
He has the potential to take
it into so many directions.
I'm certainly very much
looking forward to seeing him
just go the same
direction he's been going,
and just document those
wild places we have
that very few people ever get
to see, let alone document.
(uplifting piano music)
- As for what the future
holds, I don't know.
I don't know,
but I'm feeling very
positive about where I'm at,
and where I know I wanna go,
and the people that I have around me, and
yeah, I'm just gonna keep doing what I do,
keep being me, and see
where the road takes me.
(uplifting piano music)