Веќе некое време
пишувам за планините
и Алпските планинари.
Но има една слика
која постојано ми се навраќа на ум,
осамен човек, завиткан во ќебе ,
движејќи се низ снего.
Ettore Castiglioni ниту планинареше,
ниту пак бараше слава.
Тој се враќаше дома, во Италија.
Преку најтешката патека,
во невозможни услови.
Со месеци
немаше никакви вести од него.
Пријателите и роднините
се плашеа од најлошото.
Германската окупација се засили,
на границата партизаните и
фашистите, граничарите и бегалците,
криумчарите и шпионите,
сите се движеа во истата долина,
под истиот врв.
Седумдесет години подоцна,
смртта на Castiglioni сеуште е мистерија.
Поради тоа отидов и до едно од местата
кои му беа најдраги и го отворив неговиот дневник.
Којзнае дали одговорот што го барам
го има помеѓу странициве.
Едно светло и чисто пладне
стигнуваме до Розета.
Навистина восхитувачки пејзаж.
Висорамнината е голема и широка,
единствено ограничена од врвови и сино небо.
Погледнуваме кон Сан Мартино
со светот под нашите стапала.
Колку мал изгледа од оваа далечина.
И како се чувствуваме блиску до рајот.
Ettore, или чичко Nino,
бил најмладиот
од браќата Castiglioni
иако сите
го нарекувале Ettorino, или Nino.
Уживавме посебна врска
бидејќи беше
најмладиот чичко
и различен од останатите.
Исто така, тој се однесуваше поинаку.
Ни даваше внимание без
некоја посебна грижа,
секојпат на соодветна дистанца.
Чичко Nino имаше тежок карактер.
Тој беше тивок и осамен.
Не сакаше да се фали.
Ја сакаше уметноста.
Се сеќавам и на неговата пасија
за музика,
бидејќи ја префрли на мене.
Свиреше на пијано.
Многу гу слушаше Debussy.
The Bergamasque Suite беше музиката
којашто најчесто ја изведуваше,
Чуваше многу работи за себе,
размислуваше,
со чести напади на меланхолија.
Нешто што најдобро ја опишува длабоката поврзаност
која што тој ја чувстваше со планините и музиката.
Чичко Nino почна да оди
во планините
на многу рана возраст
со Manlio и неговите браќа.
Неговата природна способност
за надминување на
најтешките услови,
беше видлива веднаш.
Кога Manlio сметаше
дека е соодветно,
го именуваше како лидер.
На едвај 14 години,
тоа е навистина неверојатно.
Четири дена одев низ
планините и долините,
низ борови шуми и ливади,
создадени од природата
спиев во штали, пиев вода од поток,
хранејќи се само со малини
и боровинки.
Губејќи се низ шумата
повторно ја открив убавината на животот.
1930 остави голем белег
на планинарењето.
Но какво било
тие години?
Спортската техника била
најважна за потврдата
од големите земји,
помеѓу две војни,
и два тоталитарни режими,
од нацистите во Германија
и фашистите во Италија
Во планинарењето, физичките
аспекти, како што е освојување на врв
комбинирано со оние кои што се помалку физички
како храброста.
Двата фактори заедно
го отсликуваат она што го нарекуваме
„духот на времето".
Долгите и истоштувачки вежби
изведени со ентузијазам од
младите фашисти, под водство
на генералниот секретар
и придружени од планинарите
на 44 тата легија на војската,
ја одбележаа силната физичка подготовка
на Bellunese Blackshirts.
Имаше вистинско шоу на хероизам
во карактерите кои беа
поврзувани со фашизам.
The regime took possession of
mountaineering skills and techniques,
and turned them into vehicles
of political propaganda.
If we begin to talk about heroism,
heroism is pretty much dead.
Italians have become
a load of hypocrites,
in that as soon as any fascist
burns a finger on a match he
is hailed as a hero.
And the same in the mountains, heroism
has become everyday stuff.
Each rock face is unsurmountable,
every grip treacherous,
any obstacle unsuperable, a single
drop of rain a hurricane!
There are individuals like Castiglioni
who do not recognize themselves
in the spirit of the time.
There is no show of heroic spirit,
rather a retreatwithin oneself
to a much more private place.
In the diary of his early years,
Castiglioni writes,
"I would like to nullify myself
in these parts of the mountain."
There lies death ...
Yes, that is something that bears
thinking about.
At the time the only acceptable limit
was death. Death is the limit!
Beyond it, there are no limits.
His special talent was to get
physical with the mountain,
and then conquer the summit.
This style of practice became
his personal "stamp".
His mountaineering history consists of victories.
He opened up many new routes of interest
at the same time,
challenging to the art of climbing.
He used to say, the ascent,
especially the first time round,
must be conceived of as a work of art,
otherwise, it loses its meaning.
The concept of "elegance" is always
cropping up in Castiglioni's accounts.
He was spurred by a quest for elegance
in his climbing. Would you agree?
I think Castiglioni saw the
climb line as being something beautiful.
And to create something of beauty
on the mountain face,
you have not to force the issue.
You have to scout for
and follow a natural line
which is ultimately part
of nature's design.
You trained in the art along lines
pioneered by Castiglioni.
And 50 years on,
you too opened up new climbs,
so you're one of his successors.
I learned to climb by following
the example of those
who like Castiglioni have
made mountaineering history.
This is his guide to the Brenta Dolomites,
my first purchase when I was 18.
it is a bit worn now.
I spent my nights reading about the routes.
I was trying to plan the climb
in my imagination
even before going on it.
Another gem that was added to
the mountaineering campaign this year,
is the study of the mountains.
Collaborating with the CAI/Touring Club
has made me realize that
my climbing is not just
a case of selfish indulgence
but yields practical
and useful results.
Now I can proceed unrestrained,
improving the guide,
day by day, with new itineraries.
I believe that Ettore
was looking for adventure.
A desire to explore,
to visit new places.
Deep down  he was looking
for a great experience to take home.
The satisfaction in having found
the right line,
to have dreamed it up
and drawn it on the rock face.
Here in the guide, you relive it!
When he talks of his climbs you
feel it was something artistic.
An art form he wanted
to experience on the rock face
and leave for the others.
I feel increasingly more the master of
my skills and techniques because it
is no longer the urges of struggle and
conquest that push me to the top.
I love this rock, and I want to
get to know it by inch by inch.
But it is a knowledge ought to come in steps,
it should not be forced.
Only then will the mountain
reward me with the best foothold.
Today we climb
with high-tech equipment
which Castiglioni
would have found unimaginable
This equipment has been perfected
by years of testing
and we are certain it works.
But think of what they had to
use, completely different gear,
yet even so, they were able
to achieve great feats.
How important is your partner on the rope?
Your partner on the rope
is everything because you
have to trust them 100%
when you're on the face.
Castiglioni was able to climb
with the big names of his time,
like Vinazer, Gino Pisoni, Bruno Detassis,
with whom he achieved great feats
And when he moved
to the Central Alps
he teamed up
with Vitale Bramani
Both of them came from Milan
and were long-standing friends.
Together they conquered the
northern face of Pizzo Badile.
On that occasion, Vitale came up
with an improvement of the equipment.
He had the idea of replacing
the metal nails
they used to have under the soles,
with rubber ones that
promised more grip on the rock.
It's a technological innovation
still in use today,
because we have
Vibram soles on our feet when we climb.
The concept has remained
the same.
I believe that Castiglioni's
special ability was
to have the ideas and
then be able to pull them off,
seeking out the right
people in the right place
to successfully carry out
the great climb.
Sometimes evening comes and I realize
that I did not speak a word all day.
Strange, though it may seem, my day
was very enriching, in any case.
Will I become a weirdo?
I don't care,
I have no secrets,
I just want to feel free.
My return home was quite chilling,
the bottle of champagne dad opened up,
the clinking of the glasses,
the toast for my homecoming.
It was all so bland and well
rehearsed that I asked myself
why I ever bothered to come
down from the mountains.
At times I find it hard to see
the sense of my job.
Yesterday I stumbled upon
my degree certificate
I got a good mark.
But what is the point?
He graduated in law
and his father sent him to London
to get some good business experience.
But he had already decided
that a job like that was not for him.
I boldly settled that issue with
my father and he was taken aback.
He can not understand my refusing
a good job position.
They fail to understand
how you can have
any concrete and moral objectives
outside the business world.
My life is somewhere else !
Ettore liked to spend time here.
He was fond of the house,
he gladly stopped by to say hello
to my mother
When he broke his leg,
he spent the whole time here
on his crutches.
Many times he stayed over
to write his guides
instead of returning to Milan.
He came down from the mountains
with his notes
and then over here
to sort them out
and prepare them for publication.
I need the quiet in Tregnago
with its blissful peace
to take a breather.
Here is the rock I've always clung to
in my moments of despair.
Here lies my childhood,
the leaning post from where
I can start my ascent.
My dad and Ettore talked a lot about
philosophy and politics.
Hostility towards fascism in the
family was rampant from
when they had suppressed freedom
of thought and of the press.
But it was with the
establishment of racial laws
that he became
decidely anti-fascist.
He was very convinced in
his anti-fascist beliefs
even if they were only
ever expressed in words.
I always feel like I am just
passing through in Milan.
What weighs on me most is the
boring routine of city life.
Gossip, jealousy, anger,
politics and party reasoning
people who sell
themselves with no shame.
It's a set-up that
nauseates me, that sucks.
Now I also have all the bother
of accepting the medal that
if I don't, will offend all those
who have awarded it to me.
But what have they got
to do with my ascents?
They are mine
and will always remain so,
untarnished by all the gold
in the world.
A true mountaineer
could never be fascist.
The world conflict has been going
on for 3 years
Things are not going well
for Mussolini's Italy.
The allies' offensive has begun
and the top command
needs more soldiers
Ettore is forced
to leave his beloved mountains
and board a train to Aosta.
He was called as up as
Alpine Lieutenant at Aosta
in the role of instructor.
A task he carried out
with great diligence
because he liked the job.
Basically he taught the
young recruits to climb.
This is his military service record.
And we read that
Castiglioni was recalled
up in May '43
presenting himself
at the Aosta Mountaineering School
on June 11, 1943.
Called up for his by now
well-famous, technical skills
But he was based
mostly in the mountains,
at the camps in Valpelline.
Precisely. He was an instructor
and so well away from any involvement
in the command.
I got such an immediate
and friendly welcome
and my name was held
in such high esteem,
something I would certainly have never expected
in a military environment.
It struck me as a corps made up
entirely of instructors.
Their sole concern was mountaineering.
At times, one forgot about the war.
Then, with the arrival
of all the officers,
the atmosphere changed.
A look at the military's
mountaineering school
during a theory lesson
given by the instructor officer
on wooden models
of the mountain faces,
and done by the school's
better students.
Showing the various difficulties
to be faced during ascents
and the techniques
for overcoming them.
The willing pupils on the course
are all eyes and ears,
in expectation of the test.
Tests that will lead to
an arduous and intrepidating
promotion to the sixth grade,
where the conquering of rock faces and
peaks like these will be vital.
This is service he only did
for a short time,
because on September 8th
his work at the mountaineering school
came to an end.
Then the army dissolves.
And from 11th June to 8th September?
Yes, Three months.
The documents relating to that
period are unfortunately no longer available.
Did they ever exist?
On September 8th,
no documents are available
to account for
what had been going on.
One Monday morning,
I get up from my bed
and my assistant
enters the room to announce,
with the most naive of looks,
that Mussolini has done a bunker.
I did not know whether
to believe the news or not!
Far too many times had our
hopes already been faded ...
Freedom, the word that everybody for twenty years
had kept inside themselves,
like a hidden treasure.
The impossibile task of battling
on in the unprecedented fight
against an overwhelming enemy power
has been accepted.
An armistice has been requested
from General Eisenhower.
That request was granted.
On the radio just confused news.
They are saying that
the Germans have entered Aosta
It is all generally fuzzy.
Utter chaos.
My pupils are wavering
about what to do,
and many are turning
to me for advice.
I am distressed,
I almost want to cry from the desire
to do something for these soldiers.
Castiglioni took his former soldiers
to the Berio,
a summer safe house that overlooked
the valley without being seen
Ollomont was a thoroughfare,
a crossroads between Italy and Switzerland.
And for many who were escaping
war  and racial laws,
the door to salvation.
Ollomont was like a sea port,
given its border location
It was a point
of reference for the defectors
and who wanted to
go over into Switzerland.
The Berio was a very
well-known yet hidden place,
and the presence
of Castiglioni  and his soldiers
generated a certain sense of security
since the refugees
who were generally city people,
and from far away,
were definitely in need of that.
In the evening we go to Berio
to explore our new home.
We sleep in the hay,
and early morning set to work.
We build a catchment for the water,
dig out an old stove,
several benches, and wooden boards
to  make into tables and chairs.
I have written up the charter
of this small independent republic;
all our belongings and work
will be shared in common
with no distinction of class or grade.
I am full of enthusiasm.
I have a feeling that only among these friends
am I able to get satisfaction
renouncing myself for the greater
good of the community and my companions.
In Luigi Einaudi's diary notes
about his exile, he talks of a captain
who accompanied him and
his wife across the border.
Few hold any doubts about that
captain's identity as being
Ruggero Cominotti, at the
time little more than a boy.
There were two of us, myself
and another boy of my age.
One day we decided
to cross over into Switzerland
and head back up to
the Col de la Fenêtre,
unoccupied by the Germans.
En route we met a group
of former military.
They had ripped up their uniforms
so as not to be sent
back to Germany as deserters.
One of them was obviously in charge
but we were unaware
that it was the notorious Castiglioni.
They told us that
the gentleman on the mule
was an anti-fascist professor from Turin
who was being controlled
by the fascist secret police
and was bound for Switzerland
because the Germans
were looking for him.
Later we discovered
it was Luigi Einaudi.
I believe Castiglioni knew
who it was, but he had chosen
not to tell any of his
group of ex-soldiers.
I have hardly any time
to write in the evening.
For nine days I have climbed up
to the border,
but even when I'm not there,
much still remains to be done.
One thing is certain,
that being in contact with the refugees
you come face to face with what joy
that can bring.
Faces before filled with fear,
greet you at the border,
happy and carefree.
Giving people their freedom back,
helping them to flee
now gives me a reason to live!
The identities of the refugees Castiglioni
helped reach the border
still remain anonymous.
In the diary, I find only one
brief mention of an older couple with a boy,
the Bier family.
Yugoslav Jews fleeing racial laws
who arrived at Berio
after a long journey.
I find Milan Bier's story
in the archives of the Shoah Foundation.
We arrived by bus in Val d'Aosta,
on the border with Switzerland.
Wandering from one
valley to another,
till we found a way to get
into Switzerland.
We were led
by soldiers in civilian clothes,
who had deserted the army
following the German occupation of Italy.
But they were still there
on the border.
And they escorted us through
very high mountains,
Col de la Fenêtre in Switzerland.
We left at 4 am,
and got to the border at noon.
At 7pm, I came to the first village
across the border.
One afternoon I go to the
border to meet with a corporal
and exchange Swiss cheese
and wine for bread and cigarettes
Few worries, as I know him well.
When out of the blue,
there appears behind
him a border guard
I have never seen before,
pointing a revolver and who forces me
to show the contents
of my pockets and a bag.
That is how this bizarre affair all began.
So I followed the guard,
totally oblivious to
the fact I was under arrest.
I am charged with smuggling,
illegal entry, and espionage!
It seems all so absurd.
During interrogations I am
asked about a suitcase.
And then I remember the Bier suitcase.
I had left it safe in Berio
and then brought it
to the border a few days later.
But I swear
I never opened it.
When I was sent to Martigny
prison, I could not bear
the thought of even staying
there just two days.
Right from the start, I set
about thinking up escape plans,
because the investigation
was never-ending.
And at the news of being
destined for a refugee camp,
for the first time,
I became alarmed.
Now the investigation is over,
only five days are left.
No longer is there any
need to plan an escape.
The wait is over. The doors
of the Martigny Prison flung open.
And Castiglioni is escorted through
the streets of the city to the station,
refusing the offer to become
a political refugee and stay in the country.
From now on,
he will be banned from Switzerland
for the rest of the war,
any failure to do so,
punishable with immediate arrest.
Milan after the latest bombings
Every Italian on seeing the rubble
will feel
a personal sense
of destruction and loss.
Here is the La Scala theatre of Milan,
a world temple of music.
The fury of war was pelted upon it,
deconsacrating more than a
century of glorious musical memories.
So I come back to my country,
a free man,  with little to celebrate.
Not a soul at the Berio.
Only a cold and empty house
to welcome me in Milan,
and smashed windows
after the summer bombings.
A city that is devastated.
The city must have been
under curfew those evenings.
And what Castiglioni was recording
in the diary took on a new edge.
The war had changed him.
And the wording had changed, too
This week I have worked
exclusively on spreading propoganda
and helping those in danger.
Who knows when I can start
taking care of my own life again
Right now, I feel a calling towards
more important tasks.
But what were those more
pressing tasks?
Who did he encounter
in those days of frantic activity?
Perhaps members of the resistance
from whom he was awaiting news,
a signal.
Perhaps he had been out
looking for men
willing to be part of a group
like Berio.
Many names, many faces,
but not one reliable witness.
Just hypotheses, suppositions.
Of the events that followed,
he had wanted to leave no trace.
In March 1944,
the diary stops.
The one and only consolation:
I managed to bring the piano
and alongside the music
the sun has come out.
Lukewarm sun and a light breeze,
almost a mountain breeze
which fills up my lungs
How I wish to return to the mountains
and find the vigour
to act once again, be my true self.
Everything that then follows
remains a mystery to us.
After the Berio period,
Ettore returned to Milan.
And then made an attempt
to enter Switzerland on a false passport.
Exactly why we will never know.
On Saturday, March 11, 1944,
Ettore Castiglioni
leaves a group of mountaineers
and crosses Valmalenco alone by ski.
He descends the Passo del Muretto,
that borders with Switzerland, and reaches Maloja.
In his jacket pocket lies the passport
of a Swiss citizen residing in Italy,
Oscar Brändli.
I used to be a tourist and
often went to the mountains.
For the summer holidays
we went to Chiareggio.
"Is that where you met Castiglioni?"
Yes,
in the mountain refuge named Porro.
We started to talk and he said he had
been to Switzerland on a mission.
But had been captured
by the police.
He was released but told
he could not return.
This time he was definitely more cautious.
He said to me, we look quite similar,
would you lend me your passport?
If they catch me,
I'll say I stole it.
There was a mutual
respect between us,
without needing to ask too much.
The less you knew, the better.
Other comrades said he had to go
forthe CLN (National Liberation Committee).
One thing was clear,
someone who wants to enter
and then leave Switzerland
can but only be on a mission.
And it was in Switzerland
he was betrayed.
He met a person
who called him by his real name
and that aroused suspicion.
the police were called
and he was arrested.
In spite of having a long tradition
for asylum seekers dating back to 1848,
with the birth of the modern Federal State,
Switzerland becomes
a country of transit,
and especially during
the years of fascism and nazism
many people were passing
through Switzerland,
where it is clear
they were not to remain
but continue their journey
onto other countries.
We are at the end of the winter of
1944 and the war is reaching its end.
Castiglioni arrives on a fake passport
and as a clandestine.
What had he to lose?
Since the beginning of the war,
Switzerland has introduced
a visa requirement for everyone.
So entry into Switzerland without one,
is illegal.
All refugees who reach
Switzerland during the war are illegals,
and would most certainly
be sent to a refugee camp.
And the police document?
There are various reports.
A very interesting document
is this one here,
sent by the border guard to the army.
It starts by describing Castiglioni's arrest.
The corporal realized immediately
that the photo did not correspond
to the person in front of him.
Another document says,
"We talked in German
and I figured immediately
that it was an Italian refugee."
Castiglioni undergoes
questioning and is soon identified.
He is locked up in a room
at Hotel Longhin in Maloja
because it is evening and the last bus
going to St. Moritz has already left.
They take away his clothes,
shoes and backpack.
And they check on him regularly
to see what he is up to
and if he is still in the room.
Ah, thank you. Are these the photos?
Yes
Interesting
This is exactly the building
at that time.
Did you know about
Castiglioni's story ?
Yes. There has always been
someone around asking for information.
Always been a lot of interest.
Do you know where Castiglioni was held?
Yes. Right here. This is the balcony.
This one here?
Yes
My dad was called Edmondo Gianotti
but everyone called him Mondin
And he did many days
of military service during the war.
He was stationed
in Maloja at Hotel Longhin.
And one night they brought
in this young Italian man, Castiglioni.
Definitely, he lived to regret it
and was troubled by it.
Always asking himself,
"Did I do the right thing
stripping this poor man
of his clothes?"
My father imagined
he wanted to run away
because he kept telling him
he had to deliver a message.
He had probably pleaded with my dad
to let him go, but he didn't.
There is this list of names, perhaps
one of the most interesting documents.
When the police stop Castiglioni
they uncover this document in his backpack,
and ask for explanations.
And he replies, "They are people
I wanted to send greetings to."
Seeing the English Consulate in Geneva
is mentioned,
it might be assumed
that Castigliani was on a mission
to establish contacts with
the allies in Switzerland.
To take messages.
If he was on mission
for the National Liberation Committee
it was a secret mission!
So this mission
would not be documented.
When he decides
to escape his prison-room,
he had to have been aware
of the risks he was taking!
Especially half-naked!
It is true that he overestimated
his physical forces.
Even if he did possess
remarkable strength,
and likewise remarkable experience.
But attempting such a feat was
little short of committing suicide.
Reading the diary of Castiglioni
I have the impression that
in a moment of great historical
change in Italy,
Castiglioni wanted to be part
of a larger movement in the country's rebirth.
That he was almost looking for a mission.
For him, being stopped
and locked up in Switzerland
meant the end
of every imaginable goal.
And his internment would
prevent other missions from crossing the border.
The anti-fascist fighter in him seems
to be have emerged from his growing interest
in being actively involved in society,
even if not part of his nature.
It came with experience,
the contacts he made and historical events.
Something that came to maturity
only in the last phase of his life.
Letters and official documents
tell the facts,
what took place is clear.
But the reasons?
What are the underlying reasons
for this strange adventure?
I'm looking for answers
and I find only questions.
The end feels like a beginning.
And in the middle,
a man looking in the mirror
and filling page after page
in a diary.
On June 12, 1944, Vitale Bramani
wrote to his friends,
“Finally with the melting of snow last
Sunday, the deputy Prefect of Sondrio
who was aware of
Castiglioni's disappearance,
recovered the body one hundred
meters below the Forno Pass,
in Italian territory.
Findings made by the autopsy,
attributed the cause of death
to frostbite.
His death has deeply shaken
and grieved many.
The mountain climbing have lost
one of their most valued members
we have lost
a beloved friend”.
For me, I learned so much from
his integrity and discipline.
A very concrete example of creating
your own role in society.
Castiglioni died exactly as
he had foreseen and written about,
many years before.
Simply a coincidence?
The white mass recollects
itself and I am thrown to the ground
a nothingness.
Nature, once this little drama
has been played out,
reassumes its uncontested force.
Stripped by now of my human condition.
Nothing left of what
I once have been.
Only now,
in a state of total annihilation,
left to lie still amid
this vast white domain,
you realize only then,
that all of this was
nothing but an illusion.